布理 - 夏尔边境
跃马旅店
我快要渴死了 快点倒酒!
I'm dying of thirst over here. C'mon, come on!
给你
Here you are.
- 看着点!  - 对不起 亲爱的
- Watch it!  - Sorry, darling.
- 给你  - 啊 谢了
- Here you are.  - Ah, thank you.
介意我坐这里吗?
Mind if I join you?
我要一样的
I'll have the same.
做个自我介绍吧 我叫甘道夫 灰袍甘道夫
I should introduce myself. My name is Gandalf, Gandalf the Grey.
我知道你是谁
I know who you are.
是啊! 真巧啊 在这里遇到你
Well, now! This is a fine chance.
不知梭林·橡木盾来布理有何贵干?
What brings Thorin Oakenshield to Bree?
我听说 有人看见我父亲在登兰德附近的野外出现过
I received word, that my father has been seen wandering the wilds near Dunland.
我去找过 没有他的踪迹
I went looking, found no sign of him.
梭林 很长一段时间以来 关于瑟莱因的消息全都是流言
Thorin, It has been a long time since anything but rumour was heard of Thrain.
我很肯定 他还活着
He still lives, I am sure of it.
我父亲失踪之前来找过你
My father came to see you before he went missing.
你对他说了什么?
What did you say to him?
我劝他出兵埃瑞博
I urged him to march upon Erebor.
统领矮人的七支军队
To run the seven armies of the dwarves.
打败巨龙 夺回孤山
To destroy the dragon and take back the Lonely Mountain.
而现在我也要对你说同样的话
And I would say the same to you,
去夺回你们的家园
take back your homeland.
今天的相遇不是巧合 对吧 甘道夫?
This is no chance meeting, is it, Gandalf?
不 不是
No. It is not.
我很担心孤山的事 梭林 那条巨龙盘踞在那的时间够长了
The Lonely Mountain troubles me, Thorin. That dragon has sat there long enough.
黑暗势力迟早会盯上埃瑞博
Sooner or later, darker minds will turn towards Erebor.
我在绿大道上碰见了几位不速之客
I ran into some unsavory characters, whilst travelling along the Greenway.
他们把我当成了流浪汉
They mistook me for a vagabond.
我猜他们现在很后悔
I imagine they regretted that.
其中一人身上带着这个
One of them was carrying a message.
这是黑语
It is Black Speech.
一份悬赏布告
A promise of payment.
悬赏什么?
For what?
你的人头
Your head.
有人想要你的命
Someone wants you dead.
梭林 你不能再等了 你是都灵王室的继承人
Thorin, you could wait no longer. You are the heir to the throne of Durin.
召集矮人的军队 只要团结起来 你们就有...
Unite the armies of the dwarves. Together, you have the might and power...
夺回埃瑞博的力量
to retake Erebor.
召开七大矮人家族的会议
Summon a meeting of the seven dwarf families.
命令他们履行誓言
Demand they stand by their oaths.
这七支军队誓言效忠拥有国王宝石...
The seven armies swore that oath to the one who wields the King's jewel...
阿肯宝石的人
the Arkenstone.
这是唯一能让他们团结起来的东西
It is the only thing that would unite them.
而且我得提醒你一句 那颗宝石已经被史矛革偷走了
And in case you've forgotten, that jewel was stolen by Smaug.
要是我能帮你拿回来呢?
What if, I were to help you reclaim it?
怎么拿回来?
How?
阿肯宝石远在千里之外
The Arkenstone lies half a world away.
深埋在喷火的巨龙脚下
Buried beneath the feet of a fire breathing dragon.
是啊 所以我们才需要一个飞贼
Yes, it does. Which is why we are going to need a burglar.
12个月后
史矛革之战
- 敌人离我们多远?  - 很近
- How close is the pack?  - Too close.
"里格"为距离单位 1里格约等于4.8公里
不超过几里格 但这不是最可怕的
A couple of leagues, no more. But that's not the worst of it.
- 奥克闻到我们的气味了?  - 还没有 不过也快了
- Have the Orcs picked up our scent?  - Not yet, but they will do.
我们还有个问题
We have another problem.
他们看见你了吗? 他们看见你了?
Did they see you? They saw you?
没有 没看见我
No, that's not it.
那就好 瞧我怎么说的? 像老鼠一样安静
Good, what did I tell you? Quite as a mouse.
- 出色的飞贼人选!  - 你们听我说
- Excellent burglar material!  - Will you listen.
就不能听我说完吗?
Will you just listen?
我要告诉你们的是 那边还有别的东西
I'm trying to tell you, there is something else out there.
什么样的... 像熊一样的吗?
What form did it take... Like a bear?
是 差不多 不过要大得多!
Ye... yes, yes. But, bigger, much bigger!
你知道这个怪兽?
You knew about this beast?
- 我觉得我们应该原路返回  - 然后被一队奥克追杀?
- I say we double back.  - And be run down by a pack of Orcs?
有座房子
There is a house.
离这不是太远 我们可以到那里避一避
It's not far from here, where we might take refuge.
房子的主人是敌是友?
Whose house, a friend or a foe?
都不是
Neither 'en.
他要么会帮我们... 要么会杀死我们
He will help us... or he will kill us.
我们有别的选择吗?
What choice do we have?
没有
None.
快跑!
Run!
追上他们!
Abgurid!
这边 快!
This way, quickly!
快跑!
Run!
进房子里
In the house.
快跑!
Run!
快点进来!
Come on, get inside!
把门打开!
Open the door!
快点!
Quickly!
用力推!
Push!
伙计们 加油!
Come on, lads!
那是什么?
What is that?
那是房子的主人
That is our host.
他叫比翁
His name is Beorn.
是个换皮人
And he is a skin-changer.
有的时候 它是只大黑熊
Sometimes, he is a huge black bear.
有的时候 他是个强壮的人
Sometimes, he is a great strong man.
黑熊的行为无法预知 但那个人还是讲道理的
The bear is unpredictable. But the man can be reasoned with.
但是 他也不是特别喜欢矮人
However, he's not over fond of Dwarves.
他走了
He is leaving.
离那里远点!
Come away from there!
那东西不对劲
It's not natural. None of it.
他一定是被施了邪恶的咒语
It's obvious, he's under some dark spell.
别犯傻了
Don't be a fool.
除了他自己 没人能对他施法
He is under no enchantment but his own.
好了!
Alright, now!
大家睡会儿吧
Get some sleep, all of you.
今晚这里很安全
You will be safe here, tonight.
但愿如此
I hope.
现在就发动攻击!
趁那群矮人睡觉的时候杀死他们
不行
有怪兽在守护他们
我们要在路上截杀他们
他们在多古尔都集结
主人召你觐见!
统御余众 魔戒至尊
Ash nazg durbatuluk
罗网余众 魔戒至尊
Ash nazg gimbatul
禁锢余众 魔戒至尊
Ash nazg thrakatuluk
魔多翳影 邪暗深深
Agh burzum-ishi krimpatul
我们的人数与日俱增
力量也日渐强大
你将带领我的军队
那橡木盾怎么办?
战争即将爆发
你答应过我要取他项上人头的
死亡将笼罩一切
我们不追杀了吗?
博格!
我要交给你一个任务
你还渴望矮人的血吗?
所以 你就是橡木盾?
So, you are the one they call Oakenshield?
告诉我
Tell me,
亵渎者阿佐格为什么在追杀你?
why is Azog the Defiler hunting you?
你怎么知道阿佐格的?
You know of Azog, how?
我的族人是最早住在山里的
My people were the first to live in the mountains,
直到奥克从北方袭来
before the Orcs came down from the north.
亵渎者杀死了我大部分的家人
The Defiler killed most of my family.
还有些沦为他的奴隶
But some he enslaved.
不是为他工作 你明白吗? 是为了娱乐
Not for work, you understand? But for sport.
把换皮人关起来折磨 对于他来说是件乐事
Caging skin changers and torturing them seemed to amuse him.
还有像你一样的人吗?
There are others like you?
之前有很多
Once there were many.
现在呢?
And now?
只剩我一个了
Now, there's only one.
你们得在秋天结束之前到达孤山
You need to reach the mountain before the last days of autumn.
是啊 要在都灵日之前
Before Durin's Day falls, yes.
你们快没时间了
You are running out of time.
所以我们才必须穿过幽暗密林
Which is why we must go through Mirkwood.
黑暗笼罩着那片森林
A darkness lies upon that forest.
腐朽之物在树下蔓延
Foul things creep beneath those trees.
墨瑞亚的奥克和多古尔都的亡灵法师结成了联盟
There is an alliance between the Orcs of Moria and the Necromancer in Dol Guldur.
除非不得已 我是不会冒这个险的
I will not venture there, except in great need.
我们走精灵大道 那条路还是安全的
We will take the Elven road. Their path is still safe.
安全?
Safe?
幽暗密林的木精灵和其他同族可不一样
The Wood Elves of Mirkwood are not like their kin.
他们没那么睿智 却更危险
They are less wise and more dangerous.
但这不重要
But it matters not.
这话什么意思?
What do you mean?
这片区域遍布着奥克
These lands are crawling with Orcs.
他们的数量在增长
Their numbers are growing.
而你们只靠走路 永远不可能活着到达那片森林
And you are on foot. You will never reach the forest alive.
我不喜欢矮人
I don't like Dwarves.
他们贪婪...
They are greedy...
盲目
and blind.
总是无视那些他们认为比自己低等的生命
Blind to the lives of those they deem less than their own.
不过我更恨奥克
But Orcs, I hate more.
你们需要什么?
What do you need?
快走吧 趁现在天亮
Go now, while you have the light.
你们的敌人就在后面不远处
Your hunters are not far behind.
精灵之门
The Elven Gate.
这就是穿过幽暗密林的路
Here lies our path through Mirkwood.
附近没有奥克
No sign of the Orcs.
我们还算幸运
We have luck on our side.
松开矮种马吧 让它们回主人那去
Set the ponies loose, let them return to their master.
这片森林... 看起来不太好
This forest... feels sick.
好像生了病一样
As if a disease lies upon it.
没有其它路可走了吗?
Is there no way around?
除非我们多走两百英里去北边 或者多走两倍距离...
Not unless we go 200 miles north or twice that distance...
去南边
south.
阴影中有东西蠢蠢欲动 无法看清
Something moves in the shadows, unseen.
它隐藏在深处
Hidden from outside.
积蓄的力量与日俱增
Everyday it grows in strength.
要小心亡灵法师
Beware the Necromancer.
他并非表面的样子
He's not what he seems.
如果大敌归来 我们一定要知道
If our enemy has returned, we must know.
去山上的那座坟墓
Go to the tombs in the mountains.
鲁道尔高崚
The High Fells.
那好吧
So be it.
把我的马留下 我还有用
Not my horse, I need it.
你不是要离开我们吧?
You're not leaving us?
如果不是万不得已 我不会这么做的
I would not do this unless I had to.
你已经变了 比尔博·巴金斯
You've changed, Bilbo Baggins.
你不再是当初离开夏尔的那个霍比特人了
You're not the same hobbit as the one left the Shire.
我得告诉你...
I was going to tell you...
在哥布林的隧道里 我发现了一样东西
I found something in the goblin tunnels.
什么?
Found what?
你发现了什么?
What did you find?
我的勇气
My courage.
好啊 太好了
Good. That's good.
你会需要它的
You will need it.
我会在前面埃瑞博的望城之处等你们
I will be waiting for you at the overlook, before the slopes of Erebor.
注意保管好地图!
Heed the map and keep it safe!
没有我 你们先不要进入孤山
Do not enter that mountain without me.
这不仅仅是绿林
This is not the Greenwood alone.
林中的空气浑浊不堪 使人迷幻
The very air of the forest is heavy, with illusion.
它会侵入你的意识...
It will seek to enter your mind...
- 让你误入歧途  - 误入歧途?
- and lead you astray.  - Lead us astray?
那是什么意思?
What does that mean?
你们必须沿着路走!
You must stay on the path!
不要走岔路 如果你们走错了...
Do not leave it. If you do...
就永远都找不到路了
you'll never find it again.
无论发生了什么 待在大路上!
No matter what may come, stay on the path!
快走吧! 我们必须在都灵日日落之前到达孤山
Come on! We must reach the mountain, before the sun sets on Durin's Day.
这是我们找到那扇门的唯一机会
It's our one chance to find the hidden door.
这条路拐到了这边
The path turns this way.
这边
This way.
空气...
Air...
我需要空气
I need air.
我的头... 好晕!
My head... It's spinning!
- 出什么事了?  - 继续走
- What's happening?  - Keep moving.
诺里 为什么停下了?
Nori, why have we stopped?
路不见了!
The path, it's disappeared!
- 出什么事了?  - 我们迷路了!
- What's going on?  - We've lost the path!
快找路!
Find it!
所有人 快点 找找那条路在哪!
All of you, look. Look for the path!
我不记得了 这个地方好混乱
I don't remember, this place is a mess.
一点都不像是走过的
None of it is familiar.
应该就在这里啊
It's got to be here.
现在是什么时候了?
What hour is it?
不知道 我连今天是哪天都不知道
I don't know, I don't even know what day it is.
这该死的地方简直走不到头!
Is there no end to this accursed place!
瞧 一个烟袋
Look, a tobacco pouch.
这林子里还有别的矮人!
There's dwarves in these woods!
而且是蓝山来的矮人
Dwarves from the Blue Mountain, no less.
- 这和我的烟袋一模一样!  - 因为那就是你的
- This is exactly the same as mine!  - Because it is yours.
明白吗? 我们在兜圈子 我们迷路了
Do you understand? We're going around in circles, we are lost.
我们没迷路 我们一直在朝东走
We are not lost. We keep heading east.
可哪里是东边? 我们看不到太阳!
But which way is the east? We've lost the sun!
太阳
The sun.
我们得找到... 太阳
We have to find... the sun.
上面
Up there.
我们得...
We need to...
够了! 安静! 统统闭嘴
Enough! Quiet! All of you.
我们被盯上了
We are being watched.
我能看见... 一个湖!
I can... see a lake!
还有... 河流
And the... river.
还有孤山
And the Lonely Mountain.
我们就快到了!
We are almost there!
听见了吗?
Can you hear me?
我知道该往哪走了!
I know which way to go!
嘿?!
Hello?!
听到吗
Hello.
杀了他们! 杀了他们! 趁他们还活着 赶紧吃掉
Kill them. Kill them! Eat them now while all their blood is running.
他们的皮可真硬
Their hide is tough.
这只大概比较可口
This could be smushy inside.
快点搞定
Finish it off.
留活口有啥用... 杀了他 杀了他 杀了他 快!
Who needs it alive... Let us kill him. Kill him, kill him, now!
我们要好好享用... 享用... 享用
Let us feast... feast... feast.
美食... 美食!
Feast... feast!
那是什么?
What is it?
肥美多汁!
Fat and juicy!
就尝一口!
Just a little taste!
该死的! 在哪儿? 在哪儿!
Curse it! Where is it? Where is it?!
这儿!
Here!
好痛... 嘶! 叮了一口好痛!
It stings... Stings!
刺叮
Sting.
这名字不错
That's a good name.
刺叮
Sting.
比尔博在哪?
Where is Bilbo?
我在这儿!
I'm up here!
在哪里? 在哪里?
Where is it? Where's it?
快点! 去哪儿了?
Come on! Where is it?
梭林!
Thorin!
基利!
Kili!
我的!
Mine!
快点 跟上!
Come on, keep up!
没有危险了!
We are clear!
别以为我不会干掉你 矮人
Do not think I won't kill you, Dwarf.
我乐意奉陪
It would be my pleasure.
基利!
Kili!
给我把匕首!
Throw me a dagger!
快!
Quick!
你要是以为我会给你武器 那就大错特错了 矮人
If you think I'm giving you a weapon, Dwarf, you are mistaken.
搜身!
Search them!
嘿 拿回来! 这是私人物品!
Hey, give it back! That's private!
这是谁?
Who's this?
- 你兄弟?  - 那是我老婆!
- Your brother?  - That is my wife!
这可怕的东西又是什么? 变种哥布林?
And, what is this horrid creature? A Goblin Mutant?
那是我儿子 吉姆利!
That's my wee lad, Gimli!
蜘蛛都死了吗?
嗯 但还会来更多
它们越来越大胆了
这把剑来自冈多林
由诺多精灵铸造
你从哪里得到的?
Where did you get this?
别人赠送给我的
It was given to me.
不仅是个小偷...
Not just a thief...
还是个骗子
but a liar as well.
把他们带走!
Take them away!
梭林 比尔博呢?
Thorin, Where is Bilbo?
关上大门
这事儿没完!
This is not the end of it!
听到没有!
Do you hear me?!
放我们出去!
Let us out of here!
你不打算搜我的身吗?
Aren't you going to search me?
我裤裆底下可能还有东西?
I could have anything down my trousers?
也可能什么也没有
Or, nothing.
那矮人为什么盯着你看 陶瑞尔?
谁知道?
在矮人里 他还挺高的
你觉得呢?
比一般的高...
但还是一样丑
- 啊... 再来!  - 别撞了!
- Arhhg... again!  - Leave it!
出不去的!
There is no way out!
这不是奥克的地牢 这是林地王国的宫殿
This is no Orc dungeon. These are the Halls of the Woodland realm.
没有国王的同意 谁也别想出去
No one leaves here, but, by the King's consent.
一些人以为 这将是一场神圣的征程
Some may imagine that a noble quest is at hand.
屠杀恶龙 夺回家园
A quest to reclaim a homeland and slay a dragon.
我却怀疑 真正的动机并不那么高尚
I myself, suspect a more prosaic motive.
盗窃财宝...
Attempted burglary...
或是什么别的企图
or something of that ilk.
你找到了密道?
You have found a way in?
你妄图找回那颗赋予你统治权的珠宝
You seek that which would bestow upon you the right to rule.
国王宝石
A King's Jewel.
阿肯宝石
The Arkenstone.
对你而言 它的价值无可估量
It is precious to you, beyond measure.
这我明白
I understand that.
孤山里也有我想要的珠宝
There are gems in the mountain that I too desire.
白宝石 如星光般纯粹
White gems, a pure starlight.
我会向你提供帮助
I offer you my help.
我听着呢
I am listening.
我放你离开
I will let you go.
条件是将我的东西归还于我
If you but return what is mine.
礼尚往来
A favour, for a favour.
我向你保证
You have my word.
以国王的名义
One King to another.
我不会相信你 瑟兰杜伊
I would not trust, Thranduil.
伟大的王 信守自己的诺言 直到世界终结
The great king, to only his word. Till the end of all days be upon us.
你!
You!
不配得到任何尊敬!
Lack all honour!
我亲眼目睹你背叛盟友 我们曾求助于你...
I've seen how you treat your friends. We came to you once...
忍饥挨饿 流离失所
Starving, homeless, seeking your help.
可你却转头离开!
But you turned your back!
是你 弃我族人的苦痛于不顾
You, turned away from the suffering of my people.
任他们被毁灭吞噬!
The infernal that destroyed us!
愿你死于烈焰!
Imrid amrad ursul!
不要和我提及龙焰!
Do not talk to me of dragonfire!
我知晓它毁灭的力量
I know it's wrath and ruin.
我曾面对过... 北方的巨龙
I have faced... the great serpents of the north.
我警告过你祖父 他的贪婪将会带来什么后果
I warned your grandfather, of what his greed would summon.
但他不肯听从
But he would not listen.
你和他一模一样
You are just like him.
你若愿意 就待在这儿直到腐烂吧
Stay here if you will and rot.
对于精灵来说 一百年也不过一瞬
A hundred years is a mere blink in a life of an elf.
我很有耐心
I am patient.
我可以等
I can wait.
- 他和你提条件了吗?  - 他提了
- Did he offer you a deal?  - He did.
我让他等着我
I told him he could go
唾弃他的坟墓!
Ish kakhfe ai'd dur rugnu!
唾弃他和他的族人!
Him and all his kin!
好吧 只能这样了
Well, that's that then.
那交易... 是我们唯一的希望
The deal... was our only hope.
不是唯一的
It's not our only hope.
我知道你在那儿
I know you are there.
为何徘徊在阴影中?
Why do you linger in the shadows?
我正要来向你汇报
I was coming to report to you.
我以为距离上次命令清除蜘蛛巢穴 不过两个月
I thought I ordered that nest to be destroyed not two moons past.
我们已奉命清理了森林 陛下
We cleared the forest as ordered, my Lord.
但蜘蛛源源不断从南方涌来
But more spiders keep coming up from the south.
它们在多古尔都的遗迹内繁殖 如果我们能从源头消灭...
They're spawning in the ruins of Dol Guldur. If we could kill them at their source...
那座堡垒在我们的边界以外
That fortress lies beyond our borders.
守住国土 清除这些邪恶生物 这才是你的任务
Keep our lands, clear of those foul creatures. That is your task.
即便将它们赶走 又怎么样呢?
And when we drive them off, what then?
它们就不会侵入其它领地吗?
Will they not spread to other lands?
其它领地不由我操心
Other lands are not my concern.
中洲世界的命运朝起夕落
Fortunes of the world will rise and fall.
但这方国土内 我们能持久生存
But here in this kingdom, we will endure.
莱戈拉斯说你今天打得很棒
Legolas said you fought well today.
他对你很有好感
He's grown very fond of you.
陛下 我向您保证
I assure you my Lord,
莱戈拉斯只当我是卫队的队长
Legolas thinks of me as no more than a captain of the guard.
或许曾经... 是的
Perhaps he did... once.
现在 我不那么肯定了
Now, I'm not so sure.
我想... 您不会允许自己儿子
I... do not think that you would allow your son
向一个卑微的西尔凡精灵许下诺言吧
to pledge himself to a lowly Silvan elf.
没错 我不会允许
No, you are right. l would not.
但他依然很关心你
Still, he cares about you.
如果没有希望 就不要对他纵容
Do not give him hope, where there is none.
门口有精灵防守
不是所有门都有... 跟我来!
你手里的石头 那是什么?
The stone in your hand, What is it?
是一块符文石
It is a Talisman.
上面附有强大的咒语
A powerful spell has upon it.
除了矮人 任何人只要读了上面的如尼文
If any but a dwarf reads the runes on the stone,
就会被永远诅咒
it will be forever cursed.
也可能不会
Or not.
取决于你信不信这种东西 不过是块石头罢了
Depending on whether you believe in that kind of thing. It's just a token.
如尼符石
The Rune Stone.
回到我身旁
是我妈妈给我的 让我记住自己的承诺
My mother gave me it to me. So, I'd remember my promise.
什么承诺?
What promise?
我会回到她身边
That I would come back to her.
她很担心我
She worries.
她觉得我冒冒失失的
She thinks I'm reckless.
是吗?
Are you?
才没有
Nah.
上面听起来... 似乎是场挺大的聚会
Sounds like quite... a party, you're having up there.
那是Mereth-en-Gilith
It is Mereth-en-Gilith.
星光盛宴
The Feast of Starlight.
对埃尔达精灵而言 任何光芒都奉为神圣
All light is sacred to the Eldar.
但木精灵最喜爱的是璀璨星光
But the Wood-elves loves best, the light of the stars.
我一直以为它是冰冷的
I always thought it is a cold light.
遥不可及
Remote and far away.
那是记忆
It is memory.
珍贵 纯净
Precious and pure.
如同你的承诺
Like your promise.
我曾漫步于星光之下
I have walked there sometimes.
越过森林 徜徉于夜空
Beyond the forest and up into the night.
我看到世界逐渐远去
I have seen the world full away.
而纯白的光芒 渗透每一丝气息
And the white light, forever filled the air.
我曾见过一轮火月
I saw a fire moon once.
巨大的月亮从登兰德的小道边升起 金红的月光洒满天空
It rose off the path near Dunland. Huge, red and golden it was, filled the sky.
我们当时正护送一队路因山脉的商人 他们...
We were in escort with some merchants in Ered Luin. They were...
用银器交易皮毛 我们由绿大道向南
trading in silver work for furs. We took the Greenway south,
迷雾山脉在左侧绵延
keeping the mountain to our left.
紧接着 它出现了
But then, it appeared.
一轮巨大的火月照亮了道路
This huge fire moon lights in our path.
我真希望能让你看看...
I wish I could show you...
加立安 你这老混账! 我们酒快喝完了
Galion, you old rogue! We're running out of drink.
那些空木桶几小时前就该送去埃斯加洛斯
These empty barrels should have been sent to Esgaroth hours ago.
巴德正等着呢
Bard have been waiting for them,
随你怎么说我们那对酒品味极高的坏脾气国王
Say what you like about our ill tempered King who has excellent taste in wine.
来 爱洛斯 尝尝
Come, Elros, try it.
我还得监管矮人
I have the dwarves in my charge.
他们被锁着 能上哪儿去?
They're locked up, where can they go?
我敢打赌太阳升起来了 肯定快到黎明了
I'll wager the sun is on the rise. Must be nearly dawn.
我们永远到不了孤山了 对吗?
We never gonna reach the mountain, are we?
能逃出去就不会了
Not stuck in here you're not.
比尔博!
Bilbo!
附近有守卫!
There are guards nearby!
- 那是什么?  - 你先走
- What's that?  - You first.
- 欧里!  - 不是那条路 往下走... 跟着我!
- Ori!  - Not that way. Down here... follow me!
- 往哪?  - 跟上 快!
- Which way?  - Come on, go!
这边走
This way.
- 快啊  - 简直不敢相信 我们在酒窖里!
- Come on.  - I don't believe, we're in the cellars.
你应该带我们逃得远远的... 逃去别的地方
You're supposed to be leading us unknown... further away.
- 我知道自己在干什么  - 嘘
- I know what I'm doing.  - Shhh.
好吧 这边 这边
Okay, this way. This way.
大家都爬进木桶里... 快!
Everyone, climb into the barrels... quickly!
你疯了? 他们会找到我们的
Are you mad? They will find us.
不 不会的! 我保证
No, no. They won't! I promise you.
拜托 拜托了... 你们必须相信我
Please, please... You must trust me.
照他说的做
Do as he says.
现在怎么办?
What do we do now?
- 别呼吸  - 别呼吸... 你什么意思?
- Hold your breath.  - Hold my breath... What do you mean?
管地牢钥匙的人在哪儿?
Where is the keeper of the keys?
跟我来!
Come now!
干得好 巴金斯老爷
Well done, Master Baggins.
我们走 快点!
Go, come on let's go!
抓牢了!
Hold on!
比尔博!
Bilbo!
把门关上!
不!
No!
小心!
Watch out!
杀了他们! 快点!
Kill them! Quickly!
全给我杀了!
快到桥上去!
Get over the bridge!
去死!
Die!
基利!
Kili!
杀了她! 杀了那个女精灵!
矮人要逃了!
The dwarves are escaping!
追!
基利!
Kili!
诺里!
Nori!
砍断树干!
Cut the log!
邦伯!
Bombur!
陶瑞尔!
Tauriel!
等等!
别杀他 留活口
追 宰了他们!
别让他们跑了!
Don't let them go away!
哦 是你啊
Oh, it's you.
干嘛叫我来这里 甘道夫?
Why am I here, Gandalf?
相信我 拉达加斯特 我不会平白无故叫你到这里来
Trust me, Radagast. I would not have call you here without good reason.
- 这可不是见面的好地方  - 没错
- This is not a nice place to meet.  - No.
的确不好
It is not.
这些是邪恶咒语 甘道夫
These are dark spells, Gandalf.
很古老... 而且充满仇恨
Old... And full of hate.
这里埋的是谁?
Who's buried here?
如果他有名字 那也早被忘记了
If he had a name, it's long since been lost.
人们只知道他是侍奉邪恶的
He would've been known only as a servant of evil.
其中一人
One of a number.
是九戒之一
One of nine.
为什么是现在 甘道夫?
Why now, Gandalf?
- 我不明白!  - 戒灵已经被召唤去多古尔都
- I don't understand!  - The Ringwraiths have been summoned to Dol Guldur.
但召唤他们的不可能是亡灵法师
But, it cannot be the Necromancer.
人类法师无法召唤这种恶灵
A human sorcerer could not summon such evil.
召唤者不是人类
Who said it was human.
九戒只听从一人的差遣
And, Nine only answers to One Master.
我们都被蒙蔽了 拉达加斯特
We've been blind, Radagast.
在我们疏忽大意时...
And in our blindness...
大敌已当前
The Enemy has returned.
他在召唤自己的仆人
He is summoning his servants.
"亵渎者"阿佐格不只是个普通猎人
Azog the Defiler is no ordinary hunter.
他是整个军队的首领
He is a commander, the commander of legions.
我们的大敌... 正为战争准备
The Enemy... is preparing for war.
战争会从东边开始 他定会攻下那座山
Which will begin in the east. His mind is set upon that mountain.
- 你要去哪儿?  - 和其他人会合
- Where are you going?  - To rejoin the others.
甘道夫!?
Gandalf?!
一切因我而起 我不能丢下他们
I started this. I cannot forsake them.
他们现在命在旦夕
They're in grave danger.
如果你所言不虚
If what you say is true.
世界正面临巨大的危机
The world is in grave danger.
森林里的那股力量只会变得越来越强
The power in that fortress will only grow stronger.
你要我丢下自己的朋友
You want me to cast my friends aside.
有东西跟着吗?
Anything behind us?
我没有看到
Not that I can see.
- 我想我们甩掉奥克了  - 他们很快会追上来
- I think we've outrun the Orcs.  - Not for long. We've lost the current.
我们都快淹死了!
We are almost half drowned!
上岸去!
Make for the shore!
快点! 我们走
Come on! Let's go.
我没事 没关系
I'm fine, it's nothing.
- 站起来  - 基利受伤了 得帮他包扎伤口
- On your feet.  - Kili is wounded. His leg needs binding.
一群奥克在追我们呢 不能停
There's an Orc pack at our tail. We keep moving.
- 去哪儿?  - 去孤山 我们都快到了
- To where?  - To the mountain. We are so close.
中间还隔着一个湖
A lake lies between us and that mountain.
- 我们没法过去  - 那我们就绕过去
- We have no way to cross it.  - So then, we go arround.
奥克会很快就会追上来 时间也不够
The Orcs will run us down, as sure as daylight.
我们没有武器 不能自保
We have no weapons to defend ourselves.
快点帮他包扎好
Bind his leg, quickly.
给你们两分钟
We have two minutes.
敢再来一次 你们的小命就没了
Do it again and you are dead.
不好意思... 你是长湖镇来的吗?
Excuse me, but uh... You're from Lake-town?
如果我没搞错的话
If I'm not mistaken.
那边那艘驳船
That barge over there,
我们可不可以租下来?
it wouldn't be available for hire by any chance?
你从哪里看出来我会帮你?
What makes you think, I would help you?
你的靴子很旧了
Those boots have seen better days.
大衣也很寒碜
As has that coat.
你家里应该有好几张嘴要喂吧
I've no doubts you have some hungry mouths to feed.
有几个人?
How many bairns?
一个男孩 两个女孩
A boy and two girls.
还有你夫人 我想她应该是个美人吧?
And your wife, I imagine she's as a beauty?
没错
Aye.
生前是
She was.
- 对不起 我不是有意...  - 哦 得了! 别再装好人了
- I'm sorry, I didn't mean to...  - Oh, come on! C'mon, enough with the niceties.
- 你们着急什么?  - 问这个干嘛?
- What's your hurry?  - What's it to you?
我想知道你们是谁
I would like to know who you are.
跑到这里来干什么
And what you are doing in these lands.
我们不过是商人 来自蓝山
We are simple merchants, from the Blue Mountains.
要去铁丘陵探望几个亲戚
Journeying to see our kin in the Iron Hills.
你说你们只是商人?
Simple merchants, you say?
我们需要食物 供给 还有武器
We need food, supplies, weapons.
你能帮我们吗?
Can you help us?
我知道这些酒桶的来历
I know where these barrels came from.
- 怎么了?  - 我不知道你们和精灵做了什么生意
- What of it?  - I don't know what business you had with the elves.
不过看起来 结果不太好
But, I don't think it ended well.
只有镇长才能带人进镇子
No one enters Lake-town but by lead of the master.
和林地王国做生意 是他唯一的财源
All his wealth comes from trade with the Woodland realm.
为了不让瑟兰杜伊生气 他会把你们关进监狱
He would see you in irons before risking the wrath of King Thranduil.
多给他点好处
Offer him more.
我打赌肯定有不为人知的路进镇子
I'll wager there are ways to enter that town unseen.
是啊
Aye.
但那样的话...
But for that...
- 你得找个蛇头  - 我们会付钱的
- you would need a smuggler.  - For which we would pay.
双倍价钱
Double.
邪恶本就如此
Such is the nature of evil.
在大地上 无知正愈演愈烈 跋扈横行
Out there in the vast, ignorance of the world it festers and spreads.
在黑暗中孕育着不详
A shadow that grows in the dark.
这股不眠不休的邪恶力量 比即将到来的夜晚更加黑暗
A sleepless malice as black as the oncoming wall of night.
过去如此... 未来亦是如此
So it ever was... So will it always be.
届时 所有的秽物都会出世
In time, all foul things come forth.
为什么你要跟着那十三个矮人?
You were tracking a company of thirteen dwarves, why?
现在没有十三个了
Not thirteen, not anymore.
那个黑头发的年轻弓箭手
The young one, the black head archer.
我们用魔窟箭射中了他
We stuck him with a Morgul shaft.
毒素已进入他的血液
The poison's in his blood.
很快 他就要小命不保了
He'll be choking on it soon.
我问什么 你答什么 下贱东西!
Answer the question, filth!
我不跟狗讲话 女精灵!
千万别惹她
I would not antagonize her.
你喜欢杀戮 奥克?
You like killing things, Orc?
喜欢有人丧命?
You like death?
那就让我先送你上路!
Then, let me give it to you!
够了!
陶瑞尔 退下!
立刻退下
我不在乎那个矮人的死活 回答问题
I do not care about one dead Dwarf. Answer the question.
你没什么好怕的
You have nothing to fear.
把你知道的告诉我们 我就还你自由
Tell us what you know and I will set you free.
有人命令你杀了他们 为什么?
You had orders to kill them, why?
梭林·橡木盾跟你什么关系?
What is Thorin Oakenshield to you?
- 那个矮人畜生永远当不了国王  - 当国王?!
- The dwarf runt will never be king.  - King?!
现在没有山下之王 以后也不会有
There is no king under the mountain, nor will there ever be.
没人敢进埃瑞博
None would dare enter Erebor.
- 只要那龙还活着 就没人敢进去  - 你什么都不知道
- Whilst the dragon lives.  - You know nothing.
你的世界要完蛋了
Your world will burn.
什么意思? 说!
What are you talking about? Speak!
我们的时代又要到了
Our time has come again.
我的主人 侍奉的是那位大人
My master serves... The One.
这样说你明白了吗 精灵?
Do you understand now, Elfling?
你的死期要到了
Death is upon you.
战火... 就要降临!
The flames... of war, are upon you!
为什么这样做?
Why did you do that?
你保证过要还他自由
You promised to set him free.
我没有食言
And I did.
他可怜的脑袋自由了 离开了可憎的肩膀
I freed his wretched head from his miserable shoulders.
他本来还能多告诉我们些事情
There was more the orc could tell us.
他能招的都招了
There was nothing more he could tell me.
战火是什么意思?
What did he mean by the flames of war?
意思就是 他们会解放强力的武器 杀掉所有阻挡之人
It means they intend to unleash a weapon so great, it will destroy all before it.
边境 所有道路 还有河道的守卫都要加倍
I want the watch doubled at our borders, all roads, all rivers.
没有我的命令不准擅动
Nothing moves but I hear of it.
这个王国 没人能进来...
No one enters this kingdom...
也没人能出去
And no one leaves it.
把门关上!
把门封上 这是国王的命令
陶瑞尔怎么办?
她怎么了?
她跑进森林里了...
穿着铠甲 带着弓箭
还没回来
矮人的血!
他们来过这儿!
还有另一种气味...
人的味道!
他们找到了去湖对岸的方法
小心!
Watch out!
你打算干嘛 淹死我们?
What are you trying to do, drown us?
我就是在这片水域长大的 矮人老爷
I was born and bred on these waters, Master Dwarf.
就算我想把你们淹死 也不会在这儿动手
If I wanted to drown you, I would not do it here.
我受够了这个嘴碎的船夫了
Oh, I've had enough of this lippy lake-man.
要我说 我们把他从这里丢下去...
I say, we throw him off the side...
- 这样就摆脱他了  - 别这样 人家有名字... 他叫巴德
- and be done with him.  - No, Bard... His name is Bard.
你怎么知道?
How do you know?
- 我问过他  - 我不管他叫什么 我不喜欢他
- Ah, I asked him.  - I don't care what he calls himself, I don't like him.
我们不用喜欢他 付他钱就好了
We do not have to like him. We simply have to pay him.
好了 兄弟们 把钱都交出来
Come on now, lads. Turn out your pockets.
- 我们怎么知道他不会背叛我们?  - 我们不知道
- How do we know he won't betray us?  - We don't.
嗯... 有点小麻烦
There's um... just a wee problem.
我们还差十个金币
We are ten coins short.
格洛因
Gloin.
别藏了 都交出来
Come on, give us what you have.
看我干嘛
Don't look to me.
这趟冒险要把我榨干了
I have been bled dry by this venture.
我投资的回报呢?
What have I seen for my investment?
除了那些倒霉 糟糕玩意儿 还有...
Nought but misery, grief, and...
老天啊
Bless, my beard.
拿去
Take it.
全拿去
Take all of it.
钱呢 快拿来! 快给我
The money, quick! Give it to me.
等到了地方 我们再付钱 之前免谈
We will pay you when we get our provisions. But not before.
如果你还想要自由之身 就照我说的办
If you value your freedom, you will do as I say.
前面有守卫
There are guards ahead.
嘘 他在干嘛?
Ssh. What is he doing?
他在跟人说话
He is talking to someone.
他... 正指着我们
He is... pointing right at us.
- 他们在握手了  - 什么?
- Now they're shaking hands.  - What?
他把我们给卖了
He's selling us out.
老天啊!
Oh, good God!
安静!
Quite!
我们要过收费站了
We are approaching the toll gate.
停船! 货物检查
Halt! Goods inspection.
请出示文件!
Papers, please!
- 哦 是你啊 巴德!  - 早上好 珀西
- Oh, it's you, Bard!  - Morning, Percy.
- 有什么要报关的吗?  - 没有
- Anything to declare?  - Nothing,
但我又累又冷 很想回家
but I am cold and tired. I'm ready for home.
同感
You and me, both.
就这样 一切都好
There we are, all in order.
先... 等等
Not... so... fast.
受委托从林地王国
Consignment of empty barrels,
运来木桶
from the Woodland realm.
只不过...
Only...
现在桶里有东西 对不对 巴德?
they are not empty, are they, Bard?
如果我记得没错 根据登记 你是个船夫
If I recall correctly, you're licensed as a bargeman.
不是...
Not...
渔民
a fisherman.
那跟你没关系
That's none of your business.
你错了 跟镇长有关的事情 就跟我有关系
Wrong. It's the Master's business, which makes it my business.
哦 得了... 阿尔弗雷德 发发善心 大家还得吃东西呢!
Oh, come on... Alfrid. Have a heart. People need to eat!
这些鱼是非法的
These fish are illegal.
把鱼倒进湖里
Empty barrels over the side.
- 大家都听见了  - 倒进湖里
- You heard him.  - In the canal.
快点... 动手
Come on... Get a move on.
镇上的乡亲们正度日如年
Folk in this town are struggling.
时世艰难 食物短缺
Times are hard. Food is scarce.
那不关我的事
That's not my problem.
要是人们听说镇长把鱼倒回湖里呢?
And when people hear the Master is dumping fish back in the lake?
他们起义怎么办?
When the rioting starts?
那就关你的事了吧?
Will it be your problem, then?
住手!
Stop!
想做英雄是吗 巴德?
Ever the people's champion, eh, Bard?
保护老百姓 他们可能现在会拥护你 但是划船的
Protector of the common folk. You might have their favor now, bargeman,
好景不会太长
but it won't last.
升起闸门!
Raise the gate!
镇长一直盯着你呢 你最好记清楚了
The Master has his eyes on you. You'll do well to remember.
我们知道你的住处
We know where you live.
这是个小镇 阿尔弗雷德
It's a small town, Alfrid.
大家都知道彼此的住处
Everyone knows where everyone lives.
镇上谣言满天飞
All this talk of civil unrest,
有人唯恐天下不乱 大人
someone's been stirring the pot, Sire.
痛风发作了吗 大人?
Gout playing out, Sire?
湿气太重! 只可能是这个原因
It's the damp! It's the only possible explanation.
给我一杯白兰地
Now, get me a brandy.
大人 人们的情绪越来越糟
The mood of the people, Sire. It's turning ugly.
他们不过是小老百姓 阿尔弗雷德
They are commoners, Alfrid.
他们的情绪一直很糟
They've always been ugly.
他们住在这个腥臊烂臭的地方又不是我的错
It's not my fault they live in a place that stinks of fish, oil and tar.
工作 住房... 食物 总有他们抱怨的地方
Jobs, shelter... food. It's all they ever bleat about.
大人 我认为他们是被闹事者鼓动了
It's my believe, Sire, they're being lead on by troublemakers.
我们一定要找到那些闹事者 将他们绳之以法
Then, we must find these troublemakers. And arrest them.
我也是这么想的 大人
My thoughts exactly, Sire.
所有流言必须终结
And all this talk of a change must be suppressed.
我们不能让那群乌合之众联合起来 引发麻烦
We can't afford to let the rabble band together, start making noises.
否则他们下一步就会开始质问我们
The next thing you know, they will start asking questions,
成立委员会
forming committees.
调查我们
Launching enquiries.
或是用新人取代老人
Out with the old, in with the new.
什么?
What?
这是我听说的 大人
That's what I've been saying, Sire.
- 他们甚至在讨论... 改选  - 改选?
- There is even talk... of an election.  - An election?
荒唐可笑! 我绝对不会支持
That's absurd! I won't stand for it.
恐怕他们不会过问您的意见 大人
I don't think they'd ask you to stand, Sire.
缩头乌龟 忘恩负义!
Shirkers, ingrates!
蛊惑人心的家伙!
Rabble rousers!
是谁胆敢质疑我的权威?
Who would have the nerve to question my authority?
谁敢! 是谁?
Who would dare! Who?
巴德!
Bard!
你记着... 这个船夫一定是谣言背后的主谋
You mark my words, that... trouble making bargeman is behind all this.
把手拿开!
Get your hands off me!
你没见过他们 他们也从没来过
You didn't see them. They were never here.
这些鱼白送给你了
The fish, you can have for nothing.
跟我来!
Follow me!
爸!
Da!
我们家... 被人监视了!
Our house... It's being watched!
你可以告诉镇长 我今天的工作都完成了
You can tell the Master I am done for the day.
爸!
Da!
你去哪里了?
Where have you been?
父亲 你回来了! 我担心死了
Father, there you are! I was worried.
给你 西格丽德
Here, Sigrid.
巴因 让他们进来
Bain, get them in.
如果你跟任何人说起这事 我就把你的手拧下来!
If you speak of this to anyone, I'll rip your hands off!
别碰我
Get it off.
从那上去
Up there.
爸 为什么这些矮人会从我们的马桶里爬出来?
Da, why the dwarves climbing out of our toilet?
他们会给我们带来好运吗?
Will they bring us luck?
衣服可能不怎么合身 但能让你们暖和起来
They may not be the best fit, but they will keep you warm.
没有关系 谢谢
Oh, it's fine. Thank you.
矮人的风弩!
The dwarvish wind-lance!
你看上去像见到鬼了
You look like you've seen a ghost.
确实是
He has.
我们最后一次看到这种弓弩时
The last time we saw such a weapon,
镇上烽火四起
the city was on fire.
巨龙到来的那天
It was the day the dragon came.
也是史矛革摧毁河谷城的那天
The day that Smaug destroyed Dale.
河谷邦之王吉瑞安 召集他的弓箭手齐力进攻巨龙
Girion, the lord of the city, rallied his bowmen to fire upon the beast.
但龙的鳞甲非常坚硬 比最结实的战甲还要坚硬
But, a dragon's hide is tough. Tougher than the strongest armor.
只有用风弩发射的黑箭
Only a black arrow fired from a wind-lance
才能穿透龙甲
could have pierced the dragon's hide.
但这种箭却很稀少
And few of those arrows were ever made.
当吉瑞安发起最后一击时 这种箭已经所剩无几
The store was running low when Girion made his last attempt.
如果那天吉瑞安真的射中了龙
The aim of men had been true that day,
一切都会不同了
much would be different.
说得好像你当时在场似的
You speak as if you were there.
所有矮人都知道这个传说
All dwarves know the tale.
那你应该知道吉瑞安射中了巨龙
And, you would know that Girion hit the dragon.
他在龙的左翼留下了一处伤疤
He loosened a scale under the left wing.
再多一击 就可以杀死巨龙
One more shot and he would have killed the beast.
这只是一个传说 仅此而已
That's a fairy story, lad. Nothing more.
你收了我们的钱
You took our money.
那我们的武器呢?
Where are the weapons?
在这等着
Wait here.
明天就是秋天的最后一天了
Tomorrow begins the last days of Autumn.
都灵之日从后天早上开始
Durin's day falls the morning after next.
我们必须在那之前赶到孤山
We must reach the mountain before then.
要是我们没赶上呢?
And, if we do not?
如果在时限之前 我们没能找到秘门
If we fail to find the hidden door before that time,
那这次远征就毫无意义了
then this quest has been for nothing.
- 这是什么?  - 长矛钩
- What is this?  - Pike hook.
用旧鱼叉改造的
Made from an old harpoon.
- 这个呢?  - 我们叫它"柄锤"
- And this?  - A crowbill, we call it.
照着铁匠铺的锤子打造的
Fashioned from a smithy's hammer.
它拿在手里有些沉 但是...
It's heavy in hand, I grand. But...
自卫之时 聊胜于无
In defense of your life, these will serve you better than none.
我们给你钱是买武器的
We paid you for weapons.
我们要的是真刀实枪的铁家伙!
Iron forged, swords and axes!
这简直是儿戏!
It's a joke!
在镇上兵器库之外 你找不到更好的了
You won't find better outside the city armory.
所有的真家伙都被锁在兵器库里了
All iron forged weapons are held there under lock and key.
梭林 我们何不带上这些家伙什儿去偷呢?
Thorin, why not take what's on offer and go?
我赤手空拳都可以 你们也是
I've made do with less, so have you.
- 要我说 我们现在就出发  - 你们哪也不能去!
- I say, we leave now.  - You're not going anywhere!
- 你说什么?  - 有探子在监视这所房子
- What did you say?  - There are spies watching this house,
甚至镇上所有码头都可能被监视了
and probably every dock and wharf in the town.
你们必须要等到天黑
You must wait till nightfall.
梭林
Thorin.
爸?
Da?
别让他们离开
Don't let them leave.
我以为你是奥克
如果我是奥克...
你早就死了
陶瑞尔...
Tauriel...
你不可能凭一己之力猎杀三十个奥克
You cannot hunt thirty orcs on your own.
但我不是一个人在战斗
But I'm not on my own.
你知道我会跟来的
You knew I would come.
国王很生气 陶瑞尔
The King is angry, Tauriel.
六百年来 我父亲一直保护你 宠爱你...
For 600 years my father has protected you, favoured you...
你却违抗了他的命令 背叛了他的信任
you defied his orders. You betrayed his trust.
跟我回去吧...
他会原谅你的
如果我回去
我不会原谅自己
国王从未允许奥克进入我们的家园
The King has never let orc filth roam our lands.
这次他却允许奥克越过我们的边境 追杀我们的囚徒
But he would let these orc packs cross our borders and kill our prisoners.
这不是我们的战斗
It is not our fight.
这就是我们的战斗
It is our fight.
它不会就此结束
It will not end here.
它们每胜利一次 邪恶就会增长一分
With every victory, this evil will grow.
如果你父王固执已见 我们也束手无策
If your father has his way, we will do nothing.
我们只能东躲西藏
We will hide withing our walls.
过着暗无天日的生活...
Live our lives away from the light...
放任邪恶胡作非为
and let darkness descend.
我们不是这个世界的一份子吗?
Are we not part of this world?
告诉我
Tell me,
朋友
mellon,
我们何曾允许邪恶凌驾于我们?
When did we let evil become stronger than us?
你好 巴德 你在找什么?
Hello Bard, who are you after?
这里曾经有一块挂毯
There was a tapestry.
很古老的那种
An old one.
- 哪去了?  - 你说的是什么挂毯?
- Where is it gone?  - What tapestry are you talking about?
就是这个!
This one!
我跟你们说 他们是凭空冒出来的一群矮人
They were dwarves I tell you. Appeared out of nowhere.
满脸络腮胡子 个子很矮 我从没见过长那样的人
Full beards, fierce eyes. I've never seen the like.
- 矮人到我们这里来干什么?  - 这是预言
- What are dwarves doing in these parts?  - It's the prophecy.
- 什么预言?  - 关于都灵族矮人的预言
- What prophecy?  - Prophecy of Durin's folk.
预言?
Prophecy?
预言
Prophecy.
那个古老的传说看来是真的了
The old tales may come true.
巨额的金银财宝!
Vast golds and treasure!
真的吗? 银泉之王要回归了吗?
Can it really be true? Has the Lord of Silver Fountains returned?
银泉之王
The Lord of Silver Fountains.
石雕之王
The King of Carven Stone.
孤山之王...
The king beneath the mountain...
将回归他的王国
shall come into his own.
欢乐的钟声将会响起 庆祝孤山之王的回归
And the bells shall ring in gladness at the Mountain King's return.
然而世间万物将化为乌有
But all shall fade in sadness.
长湖终将生灵涂炭
And the lake will shine and burn.
- 爸 我已经尽力阻止他们了  - 他们离开多久了?!
- Da, I tried to stop them.  - How long have they been gone?!
嘘 小声点
Shh. Keep it down.
我们一拿到武器就直接往孤山赶
As soon as we have the weapons, we'll make straight for the mountain.
快... 快... 快!
Go... go... go!
下一个!
Next!
- 你行吗?  - 没问题
- Are you alright?  - I can manage.
赶紧离开这里
Let's just get out of here.
快跑!
Run!
这是什么情况?
What is the meaning of this?
我们当场抓住了偷兵器的 大人
We caught them stealing weapons, Sire.
哦 我们的敌人... 嗯?
Ah, enemies of the state... eh?
他们可能是一群雇佣兵 大人
A desperate bunch of mercenaries, if ever there was, Sire.
闭嘴!
Hold your tongue!
你知不知道你在跟谁说话!
You do not know to whom you speak!
这可不是寻常的小偷
This is no common criminal.
他是梭林 是瑟莱因之子...
This is Thorin. Son of Thrain...
瑟罗尔之孙
Son of Thror.
我们是埃瑞博的矮人
We are the dwarves of Erebor.
我们来重夺我们的家园
We have come to reclaim our homeland.
我还记得长湖镇昔日繁华的盛景
I remember this town in the great days of old.
港口停泊着满载丝绸和宝石的船队
Fleets of boats lay at harbor, filled with silks and fine gems.
那时的长湖镇丝毫不显破败...
This was no forsaken town on a lake...
这里曾是整个北方的贸易中心
This was the center of all trade in the north.
我希望看到繁华再现
I will see those days returned.
我希望重振矮人族的雄风
I would relight the great forges of the dwarves
让财富再次从埃瑞博的大殿内流淌出来!
and send wealth and riches flowing once more from the halls of Erebor!
死亡!
Death!
这才是你将带给我们的
That is what you will bring upon us.
毁灭一切的龙焰
Dragon fire and ruin.
如果你惊醒了那头巨兽
If you awaken that beast,
它会杀光我们所有人
it will destroy us all.
你们也可以听这个唱反调的 但我向你们保证
You can listen to this naysayer, but I promise you this:
如果我们成功了
If we succeed,
我们将共享孤山的财富
all will share in the wealth of the mountain.
你们将拥有黄金万两 足以重建埃斯加洛斯十次!
You will have enough gold to rebuild Esgaroth ten times over!
各位 请听我说!
All of you, listen to me!
请务必听我说 大家忘了曾经发生在河谷城的事了吗?
You must listen. Have you forgotten what happened to Dale?
难道忘了那些葬身火海的人了吗?
Have you forgotten those who died in the firestorm?
没有!
No!
这个人为什么要重返孤山?
And for what purpose?
是因为他那想成为孤山之王的野心
The blind ambition of a Mountain King,
他被贪婪驱使 被自身的渴望蒙蔽了双眼!
so driven by greed, he could not see beyond his own desire!
安静 安静! 大伙儿谁都别急着推卸责任
Now, now! We must not, any of us, be too quick to lay blame.
大家别忘了 是河谷邦之王吉瑞安
Let us not forget, that it was Girion, lord of Dale,
也就是你的祖先没能把龙杀死!
your ancestor, who failed to kill the beast!
他是对的 大人 我们都知道这个故事
He is true, Sire. We all know the story.
他射了一箭又一箭 但都没能命中
Arrow after arrow, he shot. Each one missing it's mark.
你没有权力
You have no right.
没有权力进山
No right to enter that mountain.
我是唯一有权力进去的
I have the only right.
敢问长湖镇镇长
I speak to the Master of the men of the lake.
你愿意看到预言成真吗?
Will you see the prophecy fulfilled?
你愿意分享我族的巨大财富吗?
Will you share in the great wealth of our people?
你说呢?
What say you?
我会对你说...
I say unto you...
欢迎!
welcome!
欢迎归来! 欢迎孤山之王!
Welcome and rise! Welcome, King Under the Mountain!
你知道我们少了一个人吧?
You do know we're one short?
- 波弗在哪?  - 他不在这 我们要把他留下
- Where is Bofur?  - He is not here, we'll leave him behind.
我们必须如此
We will have to,
才能在黄昏前找到大门 我们耽搁不起了
if we are to find the door before nightfall. We can risk no more delays.
你不能上
Not you.
我们必须快速前进 你会拖慢我们
We must travel at speed. You will slow us down.
你说什么呢? 我要跟你们一起走
What are you talking about? I'm coming with you.
不 不行
No, no.
大门开启时我要在场
I'm going to be there when that door's opened.
当看到父辈的大厅时我要在场 梭林...
When we first look upon the halls of our fathers, Thorin...
基利 留在这... 好好休息
Kili, stay here... rest.
痊愈了之后再加入我们
Join us when you're healed.
我要跟他一起 我的任务是照顾病人
I'll stay with the lad. My duty lies with the wounded.
舅舅...
Uncle...
我们听着孤山的故事长大 是你告诉我们的...
we grew up on tales of the mountain. Tales you told us...
你不能剥夺他亲眼见证的机会
You cannot take that away from him.
- 菲利  - 必要的话 我可以背着他
- Fili.  - I will carry him, if I must.
等你有天成为了国王 你就明白了
One day you will be King and you will understand.
我不能为了一个矮人而置远征的结果于不顾
I cannot risk the fate of this quest for the sake of one dwarf.
是我的亲人也不行
Not even my own kin.
菲利 别傻了 你应该跟大伙一起
Fili, don't be a fool. You belong with the company.
我要跟弟弟在一起
I belong with my brother.
天啊! 时间到了!
By my beard! Is that the time!
带着我们的祝福上路吧
Go now with our good will.
- 愿你们带着财富归来与众共享!  - 等等!
- and may your return bring fortune to all!  - Wait!
再见!
Goodbye!
你们也错过上船时间了吗?
Did you miss the boat as well?
基利? 基利!
Kili? Kili!
不 我受够矮人了 走开!
No. I am done with dwarves. Go away!
别 别 求你了!
No, no. Please!
没人帮助我们 基利病了
No one will help us. Kili is sick.
病得非常严重
He is very sick.
这是什么地方?
What is this place?
曾经是河谷城所在
It was once the city of Dale.
现在只是一片废墟
Now, it is a ruin.
- 史矛革荒漠  - 太阳快到中天了
- The Desolation of Smaug.  - The sun will soon reached mid-day.
在太阳下山之前 我们必须找到进山的秘门
We must find the hidden door into the mountain before it sets.
- 这边!  - 慢着 这是... 望城之处吗?
- This way!  - Wait. Is this... the overlook?
- 甘道夫说在这里会和 千万别自己...  - 你看到他了吗?
- Gandalf said to meet him here, on no account were we to...  - Do you see him?
我们没时间等巫师了
We have no time to wait on our wizard.
我们得靠自己了 走吧!
We are on our own. Come!
多古尔都
Dol Guldur.
法师的巢穴
The hill of sorcerer.
看起来完全荒废了
It looks completely abandoned.
本该如此
As it is meant to.
这个地方被施了封锁咒
A spell of concealment lies over this place.
说明大敌尚未准备好显露真身
Which means our Enemy is not yet ready to reveal himself.
他还没有完全恢复力量
He has not regained his full strength.
拉达加斯特 我需要你带信给加拉德瑞尔女士
Radagast, I need you to carry a message to Lady Galadriel.
告诉她 我们必须逼他出手
Tell her, we must force his hand.
- 什么意思?  - 我要一个人进去
- What do you mean?  - I am going in alone.
千万不要跟着我
On no account come after me.
- 保证吗?  - 好 好... 我保证
- Do I have your word?  - Yes, yes... yes.
甘道夫 等等!
Wait Gandalf!
如果是陷阱怎么办?
What if it's a trap?
转过身去...
Turn around...
不要回头
and do not come back.
这无疑是个陷阱
It's undoubtedly a trap.
藏匿于此的恶魔...
我命你现身!
我命你现出真身!
藏匿于此的恶魔...
Ce na ulco sis nurtaina...
我命你现身!
I ettuluvas caninye!
巫师来了
他在解除咒语...
他会找到我们的!
没错... 他会的
- 找到了吗?!  - 没有!
- Anything?!  - Nothing!
如果地图是真的 秘门就在我们正上方
If the map is true, the hidden door lies directly above us.
在上面!
Up here!
眼睛很敏锐啊 巴金斯老爷
You have keen eyes, Master Baggins.
肯定就是它了
This must be it.
隐蔽之门
The hidden door.
让那些怀疑我们的人 后悔去吧!
Let all those who doubted us, rue this day!
嘿 我们有钥匙
Hey, we have a key.
也就是说 某处有个锁眼
Which means, there'is somewhere there is a key hole.
都灵之日的最后一束光...
The last light of Durin's day...
将会照射在锁眼之上
will shine upon the keyhole.
- 诺里  - 好
- Nori.  - Yeah.
光线要消失了 快!
We are losing the light, come on!
安静 你拳打脚踢的 我听不清!
Be quiet. I can't hear when you're thumping!
我找不到!
I can't find it!
不在这! 根本不在这!
It's not here! It's not here!
把门砸开!
Break it down!
加把劲!
Come on!
日光消失了
We lost the light.
没用的!
It's no good!
门被封闭了 用蛮力是打不开的!
The door is sealed. It can't be opened by force!
上面有强大的魔法
Powerful magic on it.
不可能!
No!
"都灵之日的最后一束光
"The last light of Durin's day,
将会照射在锁眼之上"
will shine upon the keyhole."
上面就是这么说的
That is what it says.
我们遗漏了什么?
What did we miss?
我们漏了什么?
巴林?
Balin?
光已经消失了
We have lost the light.
我们无能为力
There is no more to be done.
我们只有一次机会
We had but one chance.
走吧 大伙 我们走
Come away, lads. Let's move on.
等等 干嘛...
Wait a minute. What...
他们去哪啊?
Where are they going?
不能现在放弃!
You can't give up now!
梭林...
Thorin...
现在不能放弃
you can't give up now.
画眉鸟敲击之时 站在灰色石头旁
Stand by the grey stone when the thrush knocks.
都灵之日的...
The setting sun...
最后一束阳光将会照耀
and the last light of Durin's day will shine.
最后一束阳光...
The last light...
最后一束光
Last light.
这就是最后一束光!
And the last light!
锁眼!
The keyhole!
回来! 回来!
Come back! Come back!
是月亮的光 秋日里最后的月光!
It is the light of the moon. The last moon of autumn!
钥匙呢? 钥匙...
Where is the key? Where is the...
刚才... 刚才还在这
It was... it was here.
它... 就在...
It was... just...
埃瑞博!
Erebor!
梭林
Thorin.
我认得这些墙壁
I know these walls.
这墙壁...
These walls...
这石块
this stone.
你记得吗 巴林?
You remember it, Balin?
房间里金光闪闪
Chambers filled with golden light.
我记得
I remember.
这里坐落着都灵一族的第七个王国
Here in lies the seventh kingdom of Durin's folk.
愿山之心团结所有的矮人保卫家园
May the heart of the mountain unite all dwarves in defense of this home.
国王的宝座
The throne of King.
上面那个是什么?
And what's that above it?
阿肯宝石
The Arkenstone.
Arkenstone.
那又是什么?
And what's that?
这个 飞贼先生 就是你此行的目的
That, Master Burglar, is why you are here.
你不能做点什么吗?
Can you not do something?
我需要草药 能退烧的东西
I need herbs. Something to bring down this fever.
我这里有龙葵 野甘菊...
I have nightshade, feverfew...
这些都没用 你有王叶草吗?
They are no use to me. Do you have any kingsfoil?
没有... 那是种杂草 我们都喂猪了
No... It's a weed. We feed it to the pigs.
猪? 杂草... 有了
Pigs? Weed... right.
别动
Don't move.
你想让我... 去找宝石?
You want me... to find the jewel?
一颗又大又白的宝石 没错!
A large white jewel. Yes!
就这样? 只是... 我觉得下面肯定有不少宝石
That's it? Only... I imagine there's quite a few down there.
只有一颗阿肯宝石
There is only one Arkenstone.
你见到了自然认得出
You will know it when you see it.
好吧
Right.
说实话 伙计...
In truth lad...
我... 不知道你到了下面会看到什么
I... do not know what you will find down there.
你不想的话可以不去 回头没什么好丢人的
You needn't go if you don't want to. There's no dishonor in turning back.
不... 巴林!
No... Balin!
我答应了会做
I promised I would do this.
我必须得试试
And I think I must try.
- 这总是让我很欣赏  - 什么?
- It never ceases to amaze me.  - What's that?
霍比特人的勇气
The courage of hobbits.
去吧 带上你... 所有的好运气
Go now, with as much luck... as you can muster.
比尔博...
Bilbo...
如果下面...
if there in fact...
真的有条活龙
a live dragon down there,
别吵醒它
don't waken it.
藏匿于此的恶魔...
Ce na ulco sis nurtaina...
我命你现身!
I ettuluvas caninye!
我命你现出真身!
Canin i sa tanuvaxe!
你来得太晚了 巫师!
已经完成了
你的主人在哪?
Where is your master?
他在哪?
Where is he?
他无处不在...
我们军团遍地!
结束了
给我追
巫师 没有什么光芒...
可以战胜黑暗
索隆
Sauron.
有人吗
Hello.
他不在家
He's not at home.
不在家啊
Not at home.
不错
Good.
很好 很好
Good, good, good.
这是什么?
What's that?
阿肯宝石
Arkenstone.
一颗又大... 又白的宝石
A large... white jewel.
这线索真明确
Very helpful.
好吧...
Well..
小偷!
Thief!
我... 闻得到... 你
I... smell... you.
我听得到你的呼吸
I hear your breath.
我感觉到你的存在
I feel your air.
你在... 哪里
Where are... you.
你在哪里?
Where are you?
出来吧... 别害羞
Come now... Don't be shy.
现身吧
Step into the light.
嗯...
Hhmmm...
你... 有点奇怪
There is... something about you.
是你带的某样东西
Something you carry.
金子打造之物
Something made of gold.
但却无比... 珍贵!
But far more... precious!
你在这啊
There you there,
阴影中的小偷
thief in the shadows.
我不是来偷您东西的
I did not come to steal from you.
史矛革 拥有无人能及的财富
Oh Smaug, the unaccessibly wealthy.
我只是想瞻仰一下您的威严
I merely wanted to gaze upon your magnificence,
看您是否像古老传说中那样伟大
to see if you really were as great as the old tales say.
我不相信那些故事
I did not believe them.
那么 现在呢?!
And, Do you now?!
是真的
Truly.
那些故事和歌谣
The tales and songs,
还远未表出您的凶猛 史矛革啊...
fall utterly short of your enormity, oh Smaug...
巨龙之躯
the Stupendous.
你以为奉承可以让你活命吗?
Do you think flattery will keep you alive?
- 不... 没有  - 确实不会
- No... no.  - No, indeed.
你看来很熟悉我的名字 但我却不曾闻到过你这种气味
You seem familiar with my name, but I don't remember smelling your kind before.
你是谁 从哪而来?
Who are you and where do you come from?
恕我好奇
May I ask?
- 我从山下而来  - 山下?
- I come from under the hill.  - Under hill?
我翻越了千山万岭
And under hills and over hills my path has led.
然后...
And... and
在空气中穿梭 我可以隐身行走
through the air, I am he who walks unseen.
令人敬佩
Impressive.
你还有什么名头?
What else do you claim to be?
我是...
I am...
幸运随身者...
Luck wearer...
- 谜语 谜语编造家  - 可爱的名头 继续
- Riddle, riddle maker.  - Lovely titles, go on.
- 骑桶者  - 木桶 越来越有趣了
- Barrel rider.  - Barrels. Now that is interesting.
那你的小矮人朋友呢?
Then what about your little dwarve friends?
他们藏在哪儿?
Where are they hiding?
矮... 矮人?
Da... dwarves?
不 不 不 这里没有矮人 你搞错了
No. No, no. No dwarves here. You've got that all wrong.
我没搞错 骑桶者
I don't think so, barrel rider.
他们打发你来做些坏事 自己却躲在外面
They sent you in here to do their dirty work while they skulk about outside.
你真的搞错了 最令人敬畏的史矛革
Truly, you are mistaken, oh Smaug, chiefest and greatest of calamities.
你很有做小偷和骗子的潜质
You have nice manners for a thief and a liar.
没有人比我更清楚
I know the smell and taste of Dwarf.
矮人的品行了
No one better.
他们为金子而来
It is the gold,
他们爱金子 就像苍蝇爱腐肉
they are drawn to treasure like flies to dead flesh.
你以为我不知道会有这么一天吗?
Did you think I did not know this day would come?
不知道总有一天那群伪善的矮人会爬上山来吗?
That a pack of canting dwarves would come crawling back to the mountain?
- 是地震吗?  - 这动静 伙计...
- Was that an earthquake?  - That, my lad...
是条龙
was a dragon.
- 爸?  - 从山上传来的
- Da?  - It's coming from the mountain.
你先走吧 带上你的孩子离开这里
You should leave us. Take your children, get out of here.
去哪儿?
And go where?
没有地方可以去
There is no where to go.
我们会死吗 爸?
Are we going to die, Da?
不会的 亲爱的
No, darling.
那条龙会杀了我们的
The dragon, it's going to kill us.
我先杀了它就不会了
Not if I kill it first.
山下之王已经死了
The king under the mountain is dead.
我登上了他的王座 吃了他的人民... 就像羊群中的狼
I took his throne, I ate his people... like a wolf among sheep.
无论何时何地 我想杀就杀
I kill where I wish, when I wish.
我的盔甲坚不可摧!
My armour is iron!
刀枪不入!
No blade can pierce me!
好 走吧
Alright.
一支黑箭 为什么你没和我说过?
A Black Arrow. Why did you never tell me?
因为你没必要知道
Because you did not need to know.
好好听着 我需要你引开卫兵
Listen to me carefully, I need you to distract the guards.
我一登上塔顶就会把箭装上
Once I'm at the top of the tower, I'll slip the arrow to the bow.
他在那! 卫兵 追他!
There he is! Guards, after him!
- 快点! 在下面! 快!  - 拦住他!
- Quickly! Down there! Go!  - Stop him!
拦住他!
Stop him!
- 把箭藏好 不要让人找到  - 不!
- Keep it safe. Don't let anyone find  - No!
- 我来对付他们 现在快跑!  - 我不能离开你!
- I'll deal with them. Now, go!  - I can't leave you!
- 布拉加?  - 你已被逮捕
- Braga?  - You are under arrest.
- 什么罪?  - 镇长说是什么罪就什么罪
- On what charge?  - Any charge the Master chooses.
- 比尔博怎么办?  - 给他点时间
- What about Bilbo?  - Give him more time.
给他时间干嘛? 等着被杀吗?
Time to do what? To be killed?
你怕了吗?
You are afraid?
对... 我怕了
Yes... I'm afraid.
我怕你现在的样子
I fear for you.
那件宝藏会带来贪欲
A sickness lies upon that treasure hoard.
你的祖父就是那么疯的!
A sickness which drove your granfather mad!
- 我和我的祖父不一样  - 你连自己都迷失了!
- I am not my grandfather.  - You're not yourself!
- 我认识的梭林会毫不犹豫进去的  - 我不会...
- The Thorin I know would not hesitate to go in there.  - I will not risk this quest...
为救一个飞贼而冒险的
for the life of one, burglar.
他有名字... 叫比尔博
Bilbo... His name is Bilbo.
是橡木盾... 那个可恶的矮人篡位者...
It's Oakenshield... That filthy dwarvish usurper...
是他派你来拿阿肯宝石... 对吧?
He sent you in here for the Arkenstone... Didn't he?
不! 不... 不
No! No... no.
我不知道你在说什么
I don't know what you're talking about.
不用否认了
Don't bother denying it.
我早就猜到了他的阴谋诡计
I guessed his foul purpose some time ago.
但没关系 橡木盾的计划不会得逞
But it matters not. Oakenshield's quest will fail.
黑暗即将来临 淹没世界的每一个角落!
A darkness is coming. It will spread to every corner of the land!
可恶的小矮人就在附近
The filthy dwarf rats are somewhere here.
我闻到了
I can smell them.
躲在阴影里的小偷 你被利用了
You have been used, thief in the shadow.
你永远只是达到目的的手段而已
You were only ever a means to an end.
胆小的橡木盾衡量过你的生命价值了...
The coward Oakenshield has weighed the value of your life and found...
你一文不值!
it worth nothing!
不 不
No. No.
- 不 你在说谎  - 他向你承诺什么了?
- No, you're lying.  - What did he promise you?
分你一份宝藏吗?
A share of his treasure?
说得好像宝藏是他的一样
As if it were his to give.
我不会放弃一个子儿 一个都不会放弃!
I would not part with a single coin. Not one piece of it!
我的牙齿尖如利剑!
My teeths are swords!
我的爪子利如长矛!
My claws are spears!
我的双翼... 强如暴风!
My wings... are a hurricane!
传说是真的
So, it is true.
黑箭确实命中了目标
The black arrow found its mark.
- 你说什么?  - 我只是说...
- What did you say?  - I was just saying...
我久闻您的大名
your reputation preceeds you.
噢 君主史矛革...
Oh Smaug, the tyrannical...
您确实是世上无人能及的
truly, you have no equal on this earth.
为了看到橡木盾痛苦
I am almost tempted to let you take it,
我差点让你拿到宝石了
if only to see Oakenshield suffer.
这样就能看着宝石毁灭他 吞噬他的心灵...
Watch it destroy him. Watch it corrupt his heart...
让他发狂!
and drive him mad!
但我想还是不要了 小游戏到此结束吧
But I think not, I think our little game ends here.
小偷 告诉我 你想怎样死?
So tell me, thief. How do you choose to die?
矮人在那里!
Dwarves!
爸? 是你吗 爸?
Da? Is that you, Da?
橡木盾不在这!
撤退!
桥上集合!
- 你把他们都杀了  - 还有其他的
- You've killed them all.  - There are others.
陶瑞尔 走
Tauriel, go.
他快死了!
We are losing him!
陶瑞尔?
Tauriel?
阿茜拉斯草(即王叶草)!
Athelas!
阿茜拉斯草...
Athelas...
你要做什么?
What are you doing?
我要救他
I'm going to save him.
- 你还活着!  - 活不了多久了!
- You are alive!  - Not for much longer!
- 你找到阿肯宝石了吗?  - 龙追来了!
- Did you find the Arkenstone?  - The dragon's coming!
阿肯宝石呢?
The Arkenstone?
你找到了吗?
Did you find it?
没有 我们要赶紧离开
No. We have to get out.
梭林?
Thorin?
梭林!
Thorin!
我要烧死你们!
You will burn!
快点 比尔博!
Come on, Bilbo!
快走
Come on.
压住他
Hold him down.
愿将赐于我之福转给他
May the blessing that was given to me be sent from me to him,
愿死神远离他
may he be released from death.
蒂尔达!
Tilda!
愿将赐于我之福转给他
May the blessing that was given to me be sent from me to him,
愿死神远离他
may he be released from death.
愿将赐于我之福转给他
May the blessing that was given to me be sent from me to him,
愿死神远离他
may he be released from death.
愿将赐于我之福转给他
May the blessing that was given to me be sent from me to him,
愿死神远离他
may he be released from death.
愿将赐于我之福转给他
May the blessing that was given to me be sent from me to him,
愿死神远离他
may he be released from death.
嘘 小声点
Ssh. Ssh-ssh.
- 我们甩开它了  - 不 它可狡猾了
- We've given him the slip.  - No. He is too cunning for that.
- 那现在去哪儿?  - 西边的警卫室
- So, where to now?  - The western guard room.
可能有路可逃
There may be a way out.
- 那里太高了 没可能逃出去  - 那是我们唯一的机会
- It's too high, there's no chance that way.  - It's our only chance.
我们只能放手一搏
We have to try.
来
Come on.
我听过精灵神药的传说
I've heard tales of the wonders of elvish medicine.
今天有幸亲眼看到了
That was a privelege to witness.
陶瑞尔
Tauriel.
躺着别动
Lie still.
你不可能是她
You cannot be her.
她在遥远的地方
She is far away.
她... 离我很远很远
She... she is far, far away from me.
她行走在...
She walks...
另一个世界的星光之下
under the stars in another world.
只是个梦而已
It was just a dream.
你觉得她爱过我吗?
Do you think she could've loved me?
跟紧一点
Stay close.
到尽头了 无路可走
That's it then. There's no way out.
我们同胞的尸骨
The last of our kin.
他们肯定带着巨大的希望...
They must have come here...
来到这里
hoping beyond hope.
在我生命的最后几天
We could try to reach the mines.
也许我们可以找到金矿
My last few days.
不
No.
我不会这样死去的
I will not die like this.
蜷缩... 挣扎着 奄奄一息
Cowering... clawing for breath.
- 我们引它去熔炉  - 它会看到我们的 必死无疑
- We make for the forges.  - He'll see us, sure as death.
如果我们分头行事就不会
Not if we split up.
梭林 我们绝对逃不掉了
Thorin, we will never make it.
也许有人能逃掉
Some of us might.
引它去熔炉
Lead him to the forges.
我们要杀掉恶龙
We kill the dragon.
若一切注定焚尽 那我们也将同赴火海
If this is to end in fire, then we will all burn together.
这边!
This way!
逃吧! 逃吧!
Flee! Flee!
逃命吧!
Run for your lives!
- 你们无处可藏了  - 看你背后!
- There is nowhere to hide.  - Behind you!
这里!
Here!
送口信去多古尔都...
橡木盾到达孤山了!
去吧!
你们! 跟我来
这边! 是这边!
This way! It's this way!
来!
Come on!
梭林!
Thorin!
跟着巴林!
Follow Balin!
快!
Come on!
梭林!
Thorin!
接着!
Hold on!
走! 走!
Go! Go!
这个计划行不通! 这些熔炉是冰冷的
The plan's not gonna work! These furnaces are stone cold.
他说得对 我们没有火能点着熔炉
He is right. We've no fire hot enough to set them ablaze.
我们没有吗
Have we not.
我不觉得你会那么容易以智取胜!
I did not look to see you so easily outwitted!
你年老糊涂...
You are growing slow and fat...
越来越迟钝臃肿
in your dotage.
懒鬼!
Slug!
躲起来 快!
Take cover. Go!
邦伯! 让火烧得更猛些! 快!
Bombur! Get those billows working! Go!
比尔博! 上去那儿
Bilbo! Up there.
听我指令 拉那条杠
On my mark, pull that lever.
巴林 你还能配制出闪火吗?
Balin, can you still mix a flash flame?
可以 只需要一会儿!
Aye, it will only take a jiffy!
来!
Come on!
我们没有时间了
We don't have a jiffy.
硫磺在哪儿?
Where's the sulfur?
你确定自己在做什么吗?
Are you sure you know what you're doing?
快点!
Come on!
拉杠!
Now!
引它去众王之廊
Lead him to the Gallery of the Kings.
不要停下来 比尔博! 跑!
Keep going, Bilbo! Run!
你以为骗得了我吗 骑桶者?
You think you can deceive me, barrel rider?
你来自长湖镇
You have come from Lake-town.
这是可恶的矮人和悲惨的长湖人...
This is some sordid scheme hatched between these filthy dwarves...
策划的阴谋
and those miserable tarp trading lakemen.
那些带着长弓和黑箭哭哭啼啼的胆小鬼
Those sniveling cowards with their long bows and black arrows.
也许我该拜访一下他们
Perhaps it is time I pay them a visit.
不
No.
这不是他们的错
This isn't their fault.
等等! 你不能去长湖镇
Wait! You cannot go to Lake-town.
你在乎他们 对吧?
You care about them, do you?
那就好 让你眼睁睁看着他们死去!
Good. Then you could watch them die!
这里! 你这个无知的废物!
Here! You witless worm!
你!
You!
我要拿回你偷的东西
I am taking back what you stole.
你什么也拿不回去 矮人!
You will take nothing from me, Dwarf!
我打败了你们老一辈的战士
I laid low your warriors of old.
在人们心中植入恐惧
I instill terror in the hearts of men.
我是... 孤山之王
I am King... under the mountain.
这不是你的王国 这是矮人之地...
This is not your kingdom. These are Dwarf lands...
这是矮人之金
This is Dwarf gold.
我们要... 报仇
And we will have... our revenge.
报仇! 报仇!
Ah, revenge! Revenge!
我要让你知道什么叫报仇!
I will show revenge!
听我说!
Listen to me!
你难道不知道是怎么回事吗?
Do you not know what is coming?
我满腔怒火
I am fire.
我... 是...
I... am...
死神!
Death!
我们都做了什么!
What have we done!
# 哦 山峦下的迷雾之眼 #
# Oh, misty eye of the mountain below #
# 愿小心看顾我兄弟之灵 #
# Keep careful watch of my brothers' souls #
# 若天际遍布烈焰灰烟 #
# And should the sky be filled with fire and smoke #
# 请长久守护都灵子民 #
# Keep watching over Durin's sons #
# 若一切注定焚尽 #
# If this is to end in fire #
# 那我们也将同赴火海 #
# Then we should all burn together #
# 看烈焰升腾入空 点亮夜霭 #
# Watch the flames climb high into the night #
# 呼唤父辈 #
# Calling out father, oh, #
# 与我们并肩 #
# Stand by and we will #
# 望猩红火光满眼 #
# Watch the flames burn auburn on #
# 席卷群山 #
# The mountain side high #
# 若今夜注定殒命 #
# And if we should die tonight #
# 那我们必将共赴黄泉 #
# Then we should all die together #
# 最后一场筵席 美酒满杯 #
# Raise a glass of wine for the last time #
# 呼唤父辈 #
# Calling out father, oh, #
# 我们将准备 #
# Prepare as we will #
# 望猩红火光满眼 #
# Watch the flames burn auburn on #
# 席卷群山 #
# The mountain side #
# 荒芜之风呼啸而来 #
# Desolation comes upon the sky #
# 我目睹烈焰 #
# Now I see fire #
# 游走山腹 #
# Inside the mountain #
# 我目睹烈焰 #
# I see fire #
# 焚毁林木 #
# Burning the trees #
# 我目睹烈焰 #
# And I see fire #
# 吞噬生灵 #
# Hollowing souls #
# 我目睹烈焰 #
# I see fire #
# 如血色摇曳 #
# Blood in the breeze #
# 多希望我能被铭记 #
# And I hope that you remember me #
# 若同伴相继倒地 #
# Oh, should my people fall #
# 那我也定会誓死追随 #
# Then surely I'll do the same #
# 孤山内殿堂幽深 #
# Confined in mountain halls #
# 我们与龙焰一同吐息 #
# We got too close to the flame #
# 呼唤父辈 #
# Calling out father, oh, #
# 你我紧紧扶依 #
# Hold fast and we will #
# 望猩红火光满眼 #
# Watch the flames burn auburn on #
# 席卷群山 #
# The mountain side #
# 荒芜之风呼啸而来 #
# Desolation comes upon the sky #
# 我目睹烈焰 #
# Now I see fire #
# 游走山腹 #
# Inside the mountain #
# 我目睹烈焰 #
# I see fire #
# 焚毁林木 #
# Burning the trees #
# 我目睹烈焰 #
# I see fire #
# 吞噬生灵 #
# Hollowing souls #
# 我目睹烈焰 #
# I see fire #
# 如血色摇曳 #
# Blood in the breeze #
# 多希望我能被铭记 #
# And I hope that you remember me #
# 若暗夜熊熊燃烧 #
# And if the night is burning #
# 我只能闭上双眼 #
# I will cover my eyes #
# 因黑暗重归之时 #
# For if the dark returns #
# 我的兄弟方已不再 #
# Then my brothers will die #
# 看天空破碎跌落 #
# And as the sky is falling down #
# 坠入这孤寂之所 #
# It crashed into this lonely town #
# 看邪影笼罩大地 #
# And with that shadow upon the ground #
# 耳边有子民惊泣 #
# I hear my people screaming out #
# 我目睹烈焰 #
# Now I see fire #
# 游走山腹 #
# Inside the mountains #
# 我目睹烈焰 #
# I see fire #
# 焚毁林木 #
# Burning the trees #
# 我目睹烈焰 #
# I see fire #
# 吞噬生灵 #
# Hollowing souls #
# 我目睹烈焰 #
# I see fire #
# 如血色摇曳 #
# Blood in the breeze #
# 我目睹烈焰 #
# I see fire #
# 眼见城镇在火光下崩坍 #
# Oh you know I saw a city burning #
# 我目睹烈焰 #
# And I see fire #
# 蒸腾的热气环绕身边 #
# Feel the heat upon my skin, yeah #
# 我目睹烈焰 #
# And I see fire #
# 望猩红火光满眼 #
# And I see fire burn auburn on #
# 席卷群山 #
# The mountain side #